<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Astro Data Group</title>
    <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Astro Data Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://astrodata.nyc/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding and tracing &#34;gaps&#34; with differential topology</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2021-05-21-gappy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2021-05-21-gappy/</guid>
      <description>We’ve been working with David W. Hogg on &amp;ldquo;How to find gaps&amp;rdquo; (or under-densities) in a data-set. Our current method relies on having a twice-differentiable density estimator (see the previous post), namely a KDE using a quartic kernel, and some KDTree tricks for rapidity (it works! So fast!).
We can find the &amp;ldquo;critical points&amp;rdquo; (minima, maxima, saddle points) using the Hessian (second derivative) of the estimated densities (i.e. on a grid).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A twice-differentiable, finite-support kernel</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2021-05-07-tha-bump/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2021-05-07-tha-bump/</guid>
      <description>With Gaby Contardo (Flatiron), I&amp;rsquo;m looking at data-mining or discovery methods for point-cloud data. Our current approaches depend on finding and relating critical points (minima, saddle points, maxima) of smooth models of the density field. These smooth models need to be twice differentiable, which is actually a pretty hard criterion: It means that we can&amp;rsquo;t use many of the standard kernels in kernel-density estimation (KDE), and we can&amp;rsquo;t use certain kinds of common speed-ups for KDE, because most speed-ups make the density estimates (technically) non-continuous.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Group meeting feels</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2021-04-30-feelings/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2021-04-30-feelings/</guid>
      <description>Our group meeting is structured such that group members add slides to a shared Google slide deck with various sections and then we go through the deck as a group. One of these sections is called &amp;ldquo;feelings&amp;rdquo; and this week most of our slides were in that section. So, instead of our usual blog post, here&amp;rsquo;s a very accurate summary of our group meeting slides with &amp;lt;3 to XKCD.
Credit for the image to Christina, with Adrian consulting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to automatically retrieve a Bibtex entry for a Zenodo record (and add it to a Sphinx documentation page)</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2021-04-23-zenodo-sphinx/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2021-04-23-zenodo-sphinx/</guid>
      <description>Niche software trick warning!
Today I have been working on overhauling the documentation theme and content for a Python package I maintain, gala, which uses Sphinx to build the documentation. On the current main documentation page, I ask users who write papers with gala to cite the JOSS paper and the Zenodo record for the version that they use, in keeping with good software citation practices.
I want to make it as easy as possible for users to retrieve the relevent Bibtex entries for gala to include in papers, so I include the Bibtex directly on the main page of the gala documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Snakemake for data reduction pipelines</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2021-04-16-snakemake/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2021-04-16-snakemake/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on a project with Quadry Chance (U. Florida) and others to infer the orbital properties of binary star systems using just the radial velocity &amp;ldquo;error&amp;rdquo; reported by Gaia EDR3. This week, I updated the group on this project, and (shockingly) I was excited to share some lessons learned when building the infrastructure for this pipeline. In particular, I&amp;rsquo;ve been using Snakemake (or, Snakémaké, right?) to orchestrate the pipeline and I&amp;rsquo;ve been finding it very useful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unresolved binaries and where they appear in the color-magnitude diagram</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-11-13-unresolved-binaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-11-13-unresolved-binaries/</guid>
      <description>David Hogg and I have been working on &amp;ldquo;open fiber&amp;rdquo; proposals for the SDSS-V surveys, which will decide targets for fibers (fiber optic cables that connect from the focal plane to the SDSS spectrographs) that are not allocated by the main survey. As a part of that, I have been making many, many color-magnitude diagrams with data from the Gaia Mission (Data Release 2; DR2). For example, look at any one of the panels in the figures above: The gray background is the same in all panels and shows the density of stars selected from Gaia DR2 in the Gaia BP-RP color and absolute G-band magnitude (these have been cleaned to remove high-RUWE sources, but if that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean anything to you&amp;hellip;ignore this comment!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Covariance of a Cross Correlation Function</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-11-06-ccf-covar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-11-06-ccf-covar/</guid>
      <description>Eric Ford summarized some of his recent exploration into various approximations to the covariance of the CCF. The CCF of Echelle spectra of stars (typically with a mask that is non-zero near the location of stellar spectral lines, but sometimes a template spectrum) is frequently used as the basis for measuring radial velocities in the context of characterizing exoplanets and binary stars. The methodology goes back to the days of measuring radial velocities with photographic plates, metal plates and photocells.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coding in Julia vs. Python (when using existing Python Packages)</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-10-30-julia-vs-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-10-30-julia-vs-python/</guid>
      <description>At this week&amp;rsquo;s meeting, I asked the group for some advice about coding in Julia vs. in Python. I am starting work on a project with David Spergel and Ruth Angus, simulating the exoplanet astrometry yield from the Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope. We are going to look at synergies between Roman exoplanet astrometry and radial velocity (RV) observations from the Terra Hunting Experiment. In order to simulate the joint RV and astrometry signals, we are planning on using exoplanet or The Joker as well as some other exclusively Python packages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of the exoplanet radius gap</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-10-24-radius-gap/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-10-24-radius-gap/</guid>
      <description>At this week&amp;rsquo;s meeting I updated the group on an ongoing project examining the influence of age on the exoplanet radius gap, a relative scarcity of close-in exoplanets sized between 1.5-2 Earth radii. The feature is widely believed to be a signature of atmospheric loss, with planets below the gap having rocky compositions and planets above the gap requiring a few percent-by-mass atmospheres to explain their low bulk densities. In the atmospheric loss paradigm, some fraction of the rocky planets are the remnant cores of planets that lost the entirety of their atmospheres.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding Unresolved Stellar Companions in Kepler Planet Hosts with Gaia</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-10-19-kicbinaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-10-19-kicbinaries/</guid>
      <description>At this week’s meeting, I updated the group about my project with D F-M, Andy Casey (Monash University), and Tim Morton (USC- the west coast one). We are looking into how to determine how the binarity of Kepler planet hosts influence planet formation. That sounds really exciting but “determine” is doing a lot of work in that sentence. First, we have to figure out which stars are (unresolved) binaries. There are a couple of different ways in which we’ll go about doing this, but the one highlighted this week is the fruit of Andy’s work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GPU-accelerated difference imaging</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-10-09-pytorch-difference-imaging/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-10-09-pytorch-difference-imaging/</guid>
      <description>At this week&amp;rsquo;s meeting I shared an update about a project called PyTorchDIA led by James Hitchcock (St. Andrews) where we are looking into how numerical tools developed for machine learning can be applied to astronomy. Unlike many applications of PyTorch, TensorFlow, etc. in astronomy, I&amp;rsquo;m not talking about using neural networks. Instead, I&amp;rsquo;m talking about using PyTorch to compute fast convolutions and matrix-vector products to accelerate more &amp;ldquo;traditional&amp;rdquo; astronomy problems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>APOGEE &#43; COSMIC =? &lt;3</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-10-02-binaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-10-02-binaries/</guid>
      <description>After arriving at CCA a few weeks ago, I&amp;rsquo;m starting on a project with Adrian Price-Whelan and David W. Hogg. We are trying to figure out how to answer the question: What does it mean that APOGEE doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a bunch of binary systems containing black holes? Barring the obvious reason that APOGEE&amp;rsquo;s targets are low-ish mass stars and thus unlikely to be companions to BHs and their high-mass progenitors, we think it will be interesting to compare a bunch of synthetic binary populations generated with COSMIC to Adrian&amp;rsquo;s close binary catalog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the Bolometric Light Curves of Supernovae</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-09-27-extrabol/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-09-27-extrabol/</guid>
      <description>I’ve been working (slowly but surely) on an open source code extrabol which estimates the bolometric light curves of supernovae from an arbitrary set of filtered photometric observations. This code is based on a package by Matt Nicholl, SuperBoL.
Estimating the bolometric luminosity and black body temperature of a supernova is an extremely common analysis problem in time-domain astronomy as it allows astronomers to easily probe supernova explosion dynamics. Unfortunately, supernova light curves are often poorly sampled across multiple photometric filters, making it challenging to build a pseudo-bolometric light curve directly from the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Great Emu Fight</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-09-18-emu-fight/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-09-18-emu-fight/</guid>
      <description>At AstroHackWeek 2020 last week, a fight broke out - not between the supportive and friendly participants, but between emulators. I pitched a hack project on comparing emulation methods, mostly so I could show this emu vs. kangaroo fight video during my pitch, and a team of fighters assembled. All credit for this project shared with Catarina Alves, Johannes Heyl, Yssa Camacho-Neves, and Johnny Esteves!
One of my research projects is on emulating galaxy clustering statistics for speedier, more accurate inference of cosmological and assembly bias parameters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How do people run big group meetings?</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-09-11-big-meetings/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-09-11-big-meetings/</guid>
      <description>Last week we had our first meeting of the new semester and we decided to try something &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo;. In fact we went back to how we ran things back in the olden days: we take the total meeting time and divide it equally between people who are online, and everyone gives an update. In many ways, this is really how we want group meeting to go. The whole point is that, since group members work on such a broad range of topics, we want to have an opportunity to hear what everyone else has been up to.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary, August 28, 2020</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-08-28-summary-08-28/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-08-28-summary-08-28/</guid>
      <description>Jiayin Dong (DJ) updated us on her project to study the eccentricity distribution of warm-Neptune exoplanets discovered using data from the TESS mission. She has discovered and carefully characterized about 100 of these transiting planets. She then uses the &amp;ldquo;photoeccetric effect&amp;rdquo; to infer the distribution of eccentricities based on the observed distribution of effective &amp;ldquo;circular stellar densities&amp;rdquo;. The inferred distribution is the observed population of orbital eccentricities but, if the detectability of the planet is correlated with eccentricity, this won&amp;rsquo;t necessarily be equivalent to measuring the true intrinsic eccentricity distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary, August 14, 2020</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-08-14-summary-08-14/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-08-14-summary-08-14/</guid>
      <description>I started this week&amp;rsquo;s meeting by asking for feedback about our plans for the online.tess.science event that I am co-organizing in September. This event is the 2020 version (hopefully this is just a year, and not an indication that it will go up in flames) of the tess.science series of workshops where astronomers get together to collaborate on new projects related to NASA&amp;rsquo;s TESS mission. The previous 3 events have all been organized in-person and, since this event will be fully remote and international, there are various challenges (and opportunities) that we haven&amp;rsquo;t experienced before.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary, August 7, 2020</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-08-07-summary-08-07/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-08-07-summary-08-07/</guid>
      <description>We had a quiet but interesting group meeting this week!
First, Trevor David shared some recent work with Gaby Contardo on looking at the exoplanet radius gap as a function of host star age and asked for feedback on methods for quantifying the gap width. He presented a few possible approaches, including fitting Gaussians to the 1D histogram of radii; fitting a line in the 2D radius-age plane by inverting the likelihood; or using a support vector machine model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary, July 31, 2020</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-07-31-summary-07-31/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-07-31-summary-07-31/</guid>
      <description>We started this week&amp;rsquo;s meeting by discussing the possibility of organizing shared group meetings with other groups within CCA or within the broader astronomical community. While this group is focused on methodology, the scientific interests are broad so it could be useful to occasionally join forces with groups focused on specific research areas of interest to group members. It could also be useful as a method for encouraging random encounters between researchers who don&amp;rsquo;t normally overlap, especially while working remotely.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary, July 24, 2020</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-07-24-summary-07-24/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-07-24-summary-07-24/</guid>
      <description>This week&amp;rsquo;s group meeting was a bit quieter than usual, but we still had some useful discussions.
Rodrigo Luger started us off with a discussion of a Gaussian Process kernel for light curves he has derived, using starry, that is parameterized by interpretable physical parameters of the target star&amp;rsquo;s surface: rotation period, inclination, active latitude, spot size, and spot contrast ratio. This is exciting because, while Gaussian Processes are often used to infer the properties of stars from their light curves, the models currently used are all phenomenological.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary, July 17, 2020</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-07-17-summary-07-17/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-07-17-summary-07-17/</guid>
      <description>Adrian Price-Whelan and Christina Hedges started off this week&amp;rsquo;s meeting with an update about the new nearby moving group that they found when looking into the pair of transiting planet systems that they discussed three weeks ago. The header figure of this post shows a color-magnitude diagram showing the likely moving group members that they identified using Gaia radial velocities and proper motions. Christina and Adrian have compiled compelling evidence that these stars are members of a previously unknown, youngish (100 Myr), nearby (~40 pc) moving group.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary, July 10, 2020</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-07-10-summary-07-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-07-10-summary-07-10/</guid>
      <description>This week&amp;rsquo;s meeting started with an update from Rodrigo Luger about his work to map the surfaces of stars using phase curves and occulations. In particular, he has been working on techniques for increasing the efficiency of his methodology when the nullspace of the problem is large or, in other words, when very little information is actually available in the light curve. He has discovered a technique that is similar to previous work by Emily Rauscher where it is possible to re-cast the inference problem into the (much lower dimensional) subspace where the data are constraining, thus drastically reducing the computational cost.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary, June 26, 2020</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-06-26-summary-06-26/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-06-26-summary-06-26/</guid>
      <description>David W. Hogg started out this week&amp;rsquo;s group meeting by sharing a project that he has been working on with Anna-Christina Eilers (MIT) to understand the systematic effects in stellar abundance measurements made by the APOGEE survey. They start with the (not totally justifiable) assumption that, while abundance will be a function of birth location, it should not be a function of evolutionary state. While this is observed for some elements (iron, for example) there are clear trends of calcium abundance with surface gravity in the APOGEE sample.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary, June 5, 2020</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-06-05-summary-06-05/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-06-05-summary-06-05/</guid>
      <description>In today&amp;rsquo;s meeting the group had a discussion about racism (in particular anti-Black racism) and our role as individuals and as a group in perpetuating it. This was an uncomfortable conversation for some group members and many of the more vocal members of the group (myself very much included) are not yet well-equipped to lead such a discussion. We spent some time sharing recommended reading lists, online educational resources, and brainstorming ideas for how to use this group to learn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary, May 29, 2020</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-05-29-summary-05-29/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-05-29-summary-05-29/</guid>
      <description>David W. Hogg started this week off by leading a discussion about how one might define a &amp;ldquo;discovery&amp;rdquo; in astronomy with a specific focus on the context of exoplanet detections in radial velocity surveys. This discussion was inspired by work he has been doing with Megan Bedell to make observing strategy recommendations for the Terra Hunting Experiment, an upcoming decade+ long survey to detect extrasolar Earth-analogs using extreme-precision radial velocities. One of the core questions is whether or not it is sufficient to define a detection as a precise, non-zero, measurement of the radial velocity amplitude.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary, May 22, 2020</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-05-22-summary-05-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-05-22-summary-05-22/</guid>
      <description>This week we had a smaller group meeting than usual (long weekend, summer weather, apocalypse, etc.), but we still had some interesting conversations!
Rodrigo Luger discussed some work he&amp;rsquo;s been doing to efficiently fit the light curves of differentially rotating stars (see the header figure). This was inspired by his collaboration with Fran Bartolić to map the time variable surface of Io using occultation light curves as discussed last week. In the limit of long lived spots, Rodrigo has demonstrated that many of the degeneracies commonly found when mapping stellar surfaces using phase curves can be broken.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary, May 15, 2020</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-05-15-summary-may-15/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-05-15-summary-may-15/</guid>
      <description>Given the current state of the world, we have been holding the Astro Data Group meeting virtually for the past couple of months and this blog has taken a hit over that time. This week, I (Dan) have decided to try to start posting a short summary of what we talk about each week so we&amp;rsquo;ll see how long I keep it up :)!
Fran Bartolić started us off with a discussion of how he is using non-negative matrix factorization to map the time variable surface of Io using occultation light curves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ambiguous periods</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-03-19-ambiguous-periods/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-03-19-ambiguous-periods/</guid>
      <description>A common problem with algorithmic determination of rotation periods from light curves is that the “best” period may actually be the undertone/subharmonic or harmonic of the true period (in other words, twice or half the true period). Two real examples from the Kepler mission are shown here.
In the first row of each figure, the Kepler light curve of a star is phase-folded on a period either from the literature or determined using a Lomb-Scargle (L-S) periodogram.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eclipsing binaries with archival radial velocities</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-03-10-archival-rv-ebs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-03-10-archival-rv-ebs/</guid>
      <description>At the TESS Ninja 3 workshop, Jessica Birky (UW) cross matched Adrian&amp;rsquo;s catalog of binary star systems found using APOGEE with the TESS 2-minute cadence light curves and found a handful of light curves with eclipses. With APOGEE cadence, it can be hard to tie down the period of the orbit, but a TESS light curve can approximately perfectly measure the period, epoch, and inclination of the orbit. This breaks degeneracies in the orbital solution and can lead to precise contraints on the stellar parameters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing a collaboration policy</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-02-28-collaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-02-28-collaboration/</guid>
      <description>Inspired by a conversation with Andy Casey who we visited at Monash University in Melbourne last week, I decided to write a Collaboration Policy, and share my feelings on the topic at our weekly group meeting.
At Monash, Andy showed me the Research Expectations page of his website, which is a document outlining the expectations he has for his students, and what their expectations might be for him. I love this idea and would like to create my own research expectations guidelines for any students working with me, current or future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STELLA - Detecting TESS Flares with CNNs</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-02-24-stella/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-02-24-stella/</guid>
      <description>This will be both my first and last post to this blog after a short (but wonderful!) 6 months at the Flatiron Institute. So I wanted to share a machine learning project that I&amp;rsquo;ve been working over the past few months with Adina Feinstein, a PhD student at University of Chicago who many of you TESS users may already know from her Eleanor package. We&amp;rsquo;ve designed a Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) named Stella that automatically and rapidly detects flares in TESS light curves at high (99%!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Occultations in reflected light</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-01-24-reflected_light/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-01-24-reflected_light/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on the problem of computing occultation light curves of planets and moons in reflected light. This is an extension of my starry code to the case where the specific intensity on the surface of the body is zero beyond the day/night terminator. To compute the light curve of an occultation event like that shown in the figure, we need to integrate the specific intensity of the body over the portion of the dayside hemisphere that is facing the observer and not obscured by the occultor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turbulence Statistics</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-01-21-turbulence-stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-01-21-turbulence-stats/</guid>
      <description>The sites of star formation are self-gravitating, supersonic, magnetized turbulent clouds. These clouds are riddled with small-scale structure - clumps, filaments, and shocks - which undoubtedly play a role in how stars form. To understand these structures a bit better, my collaborator Nia Imara (Harvard) and I have been thinking about statistics we might use to characterize them!
Inspired by the Zel&amp;rsquo;dovich approximation, used to describe structure formation in cosmology as a succession of gravitational collapse into sheets, filaments, and halos or clusters, we&amp;rsquo;ve been exploring the following space.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data viz, meeting design, and other science</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-01-13-dataviz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-01-13-dataviz/</guid>
      <description>Hello again, world! We (the data group) have been slightly deliquent with this blog lately, but our collective New Year&amp;rsquo;s Resolution is to post more. (Not really, I just made that up. But here&amp;rsquo;s hoping!) This particular post is going to be fairly meta, because coming back to the blog after a break seems like a natural opportunity to reflect a bit.
In the last couple of months we made some changes to the format of our weekly group meetings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stellar streams around the Milky Way in the Legacy Surveys imaging data</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-10-25-field-of-streams/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-10-25-field-of-streams/</guid>
      <description>The stellar halo of the Milky Way is full of debris streams — &amp;ldquo;stellar streams&amp;rdquo; — left over from dwarf galaxies and globular clusters that have been destroyed by our Galaxy&amp;rsquo;s gravitational field. These structures are diffuse, distant, and much lower density than foreground stars in, e.g., the Milky Way disk, which is why they don&amp;rsquo;t appear if you just plot the sky positions of all stars from a photometric survey like the SDSS or Pan-STARRS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Made-to-Measure modelling</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-10-11-m2m/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-10-11-m2m/</guid>
      <description>As a new Flatiron Research Fellow who stared a few weeks ago, most of my time here so far has been taken up with getting myself set up in a new institute, and a new country. But, I’ve also had time to continue some of my thesis work from a few years ago now, which involves using the Made-to-Measure (M2M; Syer &amp;amp; Tremaine 1996) technique to tailor galaxy simulations to match data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Giant planets orbiting giant stars with TESS</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-10-04-giantsorbitinggiants/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-10-04-giantsorbitinggiants/</guid>
      <description>Along with starting at the Museum last month, I also kicked off a search for (large, so probably gaseous) planets orbiting low luminosity (3-10 Rsun) red giant branch stars with TESS. First, I used MAST to create a target catalog of stars using TICv8 stellar parameters, making cuts on stellar radius and temperature which left me with ~40,000 TESS targets. I then used the eleanor pipeline in order to download individual sectors of data of targets that were in TESS sectors 1 and 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Removing HST Systematics based on Our Knowledge of K2 Systematics</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-09-28-hst-systematics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-09-28-hst-systematics/</guid>
      <description>This week, Rodrigo and I have been working on using our knowledge on removing instrument systematics from Kepler to better understand how to remove instrument systematics from HST. In my research I use HST’s Wide Field Camera 3 to observe transiting exoplanets in the infrared, and use the spectrum to try to identify water in the upper atmospheres of planets. This is a tall order, seeing as the signals we are looking for are &amp;lt;200ppm, and the instrument systematics can easily introduce correlated noise at the 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fitting single transits</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-09-20-single-transits/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-09-20-single-transits/</guid>
      <description>Shortly before group meeting, I asked Twitter what I should work on today (see above). But, working on writing the paper is much less fun than thinking about new features so I went through a derivation of the right &amp;ldquo;priors&amp;rdquo; to use when characterizing a single transit. I have previously published on this topic (as have many others!) and the basic idea is that even if you only detect a single transit you can place some constraint on the orbital period because the duration of the transit is informative.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding Anomalies in Galaxy Surveys</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-08-23-anomalies/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-08-23-anomalies/</guid>
      <description>I have been working on a new method for detecting anomalies in astronomical images with deep learning, with Marc Huertas-Company (Observatoire de Paris) and Alexie Leauthaud (UCSC). The idea is to use unsupervised learning to pick out potentially interesting (or &amp;ldquo;anomalous&amp;rdquo;) objects in galaxy surveys, as there is way too much data to look through by hand; the lack of supervision also means we can find interesting things we may not know to look for.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Transition Redshift</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-08-16-ztran/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-08-16-ztran/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m working on a short reionization project where we want to figure out where a function crosses zero. I&amp;rsquo;ll spare the details of what this function (P21,g) is for the bottom of this post. But suffice it to say that the redshift where it transitions from being positive to negative (the &amp;ldquo;transition redshift&amp;rdquo;) is an interesting quantity. The plot shows a sketch of what the data might look like - where the function itself is not measured but the data still constrai</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Doppler Imaging</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-08-09-doppler/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-08-09-doppler/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m generally interested in the problem of mapping the surfaces of stars and exoplanets, and while I&amp;rsquo;ve focused so far on doing this using photometric timeseries, for the past couple months I&amp;rsquo;ve been tinkering with spectroscopic data and the idea of Doppler imaging. The basic idea here is to take high resolution spectra of a rapidly rotating star at different rotational phases and look at the distortion of its spectral lines as starspots rotate from the blueshifted hemisphere to the redshifted hemisphere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python Toolkit for Background-Subtracted TESS Lightcurves</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-08-02-tess_cpm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-08-02-tess_cpm/</guid>
      <description>Over the summer I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with Dan Foreman-Mackey and David Hogg on developing a Python toolkit to obtain background-subtracted TESS lightcurves from the Full-Frame Images (FFI). One of the goals of this project is to detect transient events in the TESS data by doing difference imaging without constructing a reference image. We do that by implementing a method called Causal Pixel Model (CPM) Difference Imaging explained in detail here and here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The straight stellar stream in Cen A</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-07-26-cena/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-07-26-cena/</guid>
      <description>I recently attended the IAU Symposium 355 “The Realm of the Low Surface Brightness Universe”, where I had the chance to get an update on the current observational status of, among other things, detecting streams in external galaxies. Denija Crnojevic showed her map (Crnojevic et al. 2016) of the nearby galaxy, Centaurus A (see left panel of the Figure above). This lead to some discussion on the “straightness” of the stellar stream emerging from the dwarf galaxy referred to as Dw3 in the figure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dust Inference</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-07-19-cmd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-07-19-cmd/</guid>
      <description>I have been working with Andy Miller (Columbia) on building a 3D dust map of the Milky Way galaxy using a Gaussian process prior on 1e9 stars from Gaia. Of course we always want to solve all of astronomy, and infer the dust map and the color magnitude diagram simultaneously. But for a first step we want to model a dust-free CMD, infer individual dust estimates for stars, and then build the GP model on these individual estimates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to our blog!</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-07-12-welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-07-12-welcome/</guid>
      <description>This is the first post for our site and it&amp;rsquo;s pretty meta. This week at group meeting, I presented this blog to the group (pictured above). Our goal is to use this as a way to highlight some of the things that we work on in our group, to give ourselves some amount of accountability, and to practice open and transparent science. After this post, the plan is that each week one group member will post the figure that they presented in group meeting with a short description of what they&amp;rsquo;re working on, what they&amp;rsquo;ve recently learned, and (perhaps) where they&amp;rsquo;re stuck.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-07-06-hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2019-07-06-hello-world/</guid>
      <description>This is our website where one member of the group will post a research update every week. This is meant to be work in progress so keep your expectations set accordingly.
Photo by Anthony DELANOIX on Unsplash.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>