<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Trevor David on Astro Data Group</title>
    <link>https://astrodata.nyc/authors/trevor-david/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Trevor David on Astro Data Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://astrodata.nyc/authors/trevor-david/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of the exoplanet radius gap</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-10-24-radius-gap/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-10-24-radius-gap/</guid>
      <description>At this week&amp;rsquo;s meeting I updated the group on an ongoing project examining the influence of age on the exoplanet radius gap, a relative scarcity of close-in exoplanets sized between 1.5-2 Earth radii. The feature is widely believed to be a signature of atmospheric loss, with planets below the gap having rocky compositions and planets above the gap requiring a few percent-by-mass atmospheres to explain their low bulk densities. In the atmospheric loss paradigm, some fraction of the rocky planets are the remnant cores of planets that lost the entirety of their atmospheres.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ambiguous periods</title>
      <link>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-03-19-ambiguous-periods/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astrodata.nyc/posts/2020-03-19-ambiguous-periods/</guid>
      <description>A common problem with algorithmic determination of rotation periods from light curves is that the “best” period may actually be the undertone/subharmonic or harmonic of the true period (in other words, twice or half the true period). Two real examples from the Kepler mission are shown here.
In the first row of each figure, the Kepler light curve of a star is phase-folded on a period either from the literature or determined using a Lomb-Scargle (L-S) periodogram.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>